

# Dr. George Alestas

Physicist - Researcher

### Affiliation Instituto de Fisica Teorica (IFT), CSIC

# **Professional Summary**

Collaborations

LIGO VIRGO LISA A highly motivated researcher specializing in Cosmology and Astrophysics. I am proficient in the theoretical and numerical exploration of cosmological models, including cosmological parameter inference using various well-known MCMC software. I have worked on several aspects of the Hubble and  $S_8$  tensions. Part of the LIGO, Virgo and LISA collaborations. I would describe myself as a fast learner and an excellent collaborator.

### **Education**

Website

georgealestas.github.io

2022 - Now **Postdoctoral Studies**Instituto de Fisica Teorica (IFT), Madrid

2018 - 2022 **PhD in Cosmology** 

University of Ioannina

Universidad Autónoma de Madrid

PhD Thesis: "ΛCDM and the Implications of the Hubble Tension" Advisor: Prof. Leandros Perivolaropoulos

Grade: Summa Cum Laude

**Tel & Skype** (+30) 6989964269

alestasg

E-mail

2015 - 2017 MSc in Theoretical Physics

University of Patras

Upper First Class Honours, GPA was 8.87/10.

MSc Thesis: "Thermodynamic Properties of Self-Gravitating Systems",

Grade: 10/10

alestasg@gmail.com

2010 - 2014 **BSc in Physics** 

University of Patras

Upper Second Class Honours, top 4 percent of my class. My specialization was Theoretical and Mathematical Physics, Astronomy and Astrophysics. Specialization courses GPA was 8,36/10.

BSc Thesis: "Cosmological Perturbation Theory and Gravitational Waves", Grade: 10/10, indicative courses and grades:

1. Astrophysics I: 8/10

2. Astrophysics II: 8.5/10

3. Computational Physics: 9.5/10

4. Elementary Particles and Cosmology: 8/10

# **Publication Record**

Nine papers (highlighted most important) with a total of more than 520 citations and **h-index** = **9**, two articles published in conference proceedings and one N-author review. The codes used in the analysis of all the papers are publicly available at **GitHub**. Click **here** for my up to date InspireHEP profile.

- 1. Machine learning constraints on deviations from general relativity from the large scale structure of the Universe, G. Alestas, L. Kazantzidis and S. Nesseris, Phys.Rev.D 106 (2022) 10, 10, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.106.103519
- 2. Constraining a late time transition of  $G_{\rm eff}$  using low-z galaxy survey data, G. Alestas, L. Perivolaropoulos and K. Tanidis, Phys.Rev.D 106 (2022) 2, 023526, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.106.023526 (More than 10 citations)
- 3. Late-transition vs smooth H(z) deformation models for the resolution of the **Hubble crisis**, G. Alestas, D. Camarena, E. Di Valentino, L. Kazantzidis, V. Marra, S. Nesseris and L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 105 (2022) 6, 063538, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.105.063538 (More than 35 citations)

# Languages

Greek → Native English → Fluent

- 4. Hints for a gravitational constant transition in Tully-Fisher data, G. Alestas, I. Antoniou and L. Perivolaropoulos, Universe 7 (2021) 366, DOI: 10.3390/universe7100366, (More than 20 citations)
- 5. Late time approaches to the Hubble tension deforming H(z), worsen the growth tension, G. Alestas, L. Perivolaropoulos, Mon.Not.Roy.Astron.Soc. 504 (2021) 3, 3956-3962, DOI: 10.1093/mnras/stab1070, (More than 40 citations)
- 6. **A** *w*-*M* **phantom transition at zt<0.1 as a resolution of the Hubble tension**, G. Alestas, L. Kazantzidis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 103 (2021) 8, 083517, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.103.083517, (More than 40 citations)
- 7. Existence and Stability of Static Spherical Fluid Shells in a Schwarzschild-Rindler-anti-de Sitter Metric, G. Alestas, G.V. Kraniotis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 102 (2020) 104015, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.102.104015, (More than 10 citations)
- 8.  $H_0$  tension, phantom dark energy, and cosmological parameter degeneracies, G. Alestas, L. Kazantzidis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 101 (2020) 12, 123516, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.101.123516, (More than 90 citations)
- 9. Evading Derrick's theorem in curved space: Static metastable spherical domain wall, Alestas G., Perivolaropoulos L., Phys.Rev.D 99 (2019) no.6, 064026, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.99.064026, (More than 10 citations)

Articles published in conference proceedings:

- 1. **Stable, Spherical and Thin Fluid Shells,** G. Alestas, G. V. Kraniotis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Published in Phys.Sci.Forum 2021, 2, 24, DOI: 10.3390/ECU2021-09332
- An Overview of Nonstandard Signals in Cosmological Data, G. Alestas, G. V. Kraniotis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Published in Phys.Sci.Forum 2021, 2, 28, DOI: 10.3390/ECU2021-09333

#### N-author articles:

 Cosmology Intertwined: A Review of the Particle Physics, Astrophysics, and Cosmology Associated with the Cosmological Tensions and Anomalies, E. Di Valentino et al., Contribution to: 2022 Snowmass Summer Study, Published in JHEAp 34 (2022) 49-211, DOI: 10.1016/j.jheap.2022.04.002, (More than 250 citations)

# **Scholarships & Grants**

- Fellow of the Greek State and the European Union (European Social Fund ESF) through the Operational Programme "Competitiveness, Entrepreneurship and Innovation 2014-2020 (EPAnEK)"
- Fellow of the Greek State and the European Union (European Social Fund ESF) through the Operational Programme "Human Resources Development, Education and Lifelong Learning 2014-2020"
- European Cooperation in Science & Technology (COST) grant for a short term scientific mission (STSM) in the context of the action "CA15117 Cosmology and Astrophysics Network for Theoretical Advances and Training Actions (CANTATA)" and the project "Search for Hints of Modified Gravity in Cosmological Data"

## **Conferences Attended & Talks Given**

- HEP 2020 38th Conference on Recent Developments in High Energy Physics and Cosmology, September 2021, Athens, Greece.
- 16th Marcel Grossmann Meeting MG16, July 2021, Rome, Italy, (Talk)
- 19th online Conference in the String Phenomenology Conference Series, June 2020, Boston, United States.
- 9th Korea Institute of Advanced Study (KIAS) Workshop on Cosmology and Structure Formation webinar, November 2020, Seoul, South Korea
- Workshop on Quantum Fields and Nonlinear Phenomena, SEENET-MTP-CERN-ICTP Joint Meeting, 2020, Romania, (Talk)
- SEENET-MTP Balkan School on High Energy and Particle Physics: Theory and Phenomenology, 2019, Ioannina, (Talk)
- HEP 2019 Recent Developments on High Energy Physics and Cosmology, 2019, Athens

### **Research Interests**

Theoretical Cosmology, Observational Cosmology, Hubble Tension, Modified Gravity Theories, Dark Energy, Data Analysis, Gravitational waves, Soliton Physics.

# **Programming Knowledge**

- Linux, Windows
- Python, C/C++, Fortran, HTML, Tensorflow
- COSMOMC/CAMB, MontePython/Class, Mathematica, Matlab

### **Skills**

Cosmology, Theoretical Astrophysics, Computational Physics, General Relativity, Data Analysis

### **Referee Work**

I am a referee for the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS) journal. For more details please click **here** to visit my Publons profile.

# **Teaching Experience**

#### 2021-22 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Classical Electrodynamics I (5th Semester Core Course - 52), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments.

#### 2021-22 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Gravity and General Theory of Relativity (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course – 106), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

### 2020-21 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Cosmology (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course - 105), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2020-21 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Gravity and General Theory of Relativity (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course – 106), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

### 2019-20 Teaching Assistant

University of Ioannina

Classical Electrodynamics I (5th Semester Core Course – 52), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2016-17 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Patras

Astrophysics Laboratory (TAE450), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third and fourth year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2016-17 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Patras

Astronomy Laboratory (TAE451), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third and fourth year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.
- 3. Demonstrating the use of Astronomical equipment.

### **Societies**

- Student Member of the American Physical Society (APS)
- Junior Member of the Hellenic Society on Relativity, Gravitation and Cosmology

# **Professional References**

Prof. Leandros Perivolaropoulos - leandros@uoi.gr (PhD Advisor)

Dr. Sachiko Kuroyanagi - sachiko.kuroyanagi@csic.es

Asst. Prof. Savvas Nesseris - savvas.nesseris@csic.es

Dr. Eleonora Di Valentino - E.Divalentino@shef.ac.uk

Asst. Prof. Panagiota E. Christopoulou - pechris@physics.upatras.gr